Guide to the Stanford University, Engineering Case Program, Case Files SC0269
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Case studies
  - Hoover Dam, H. O. Fuchs, P. Searles, UCLA, 1964; ECL 1-17; Total 33 pages with 16 text, 17 exhibits.
    Taken from published sources plus interviews with former engineers of the project, this historical description was prepared to illustrate engineering design and its role in society for a freshman.
  - Hewlett-Packard Company 1, (A) Mechanical Design of Coaxial Microwave Connectors, (B) History of Coaxial Microwave Connector Design, K. H. Vesper, (C) Commercial Development of the Sexless Connector by Amphenol Corporation, Sue Hays, 1964, 1967; ECL 1; Total 65 pages (Parts A, B, C) with 16 text, 49 exhibits.
    Anthony Badger, a mechanical engineer has been asked by his management for the mechanical design of a better coaxial connector for microwave frequencies. Part A relates the situation which he faced. Part B of the case shows how Mr. Badger approached the problem, his idea sketches and his detail work. Part C shows the redesign done by Amphenol who purchased the patent and marketed the connector.
  - Hewlett-Packard Company III, (A) Drill Jig Design for a Structural Plate, (B) Drill Jig Tolerances, P. Z. Bulkeley, E. Echterling, 1964; ECL 15; Total 43 pages (Parts A,B) with 9 text, 34 exhibits.
    Part A describes a situation at Hewlett-Packard in which a drill jig is needed. Part (B) is a sequel showing a company engineer's layout of the solution for which precise dimensional tolerances remain to be determined. Part A alone can be used as a design problem. Students could later be given Part B to compare their solutions with a professional's. Or for a drawing problem alone both parts could be handed out together for students to work out the tolerances and put on dimensions. Background description includes how the problem came up, what the jig has to do with manufacturing, and why there is need for solution.
  - Pacific Gas and Electric Company, Digital Computer Simulation of a Hydroelectric Plant, R. E. Keller, R. D. Regier, 1964; ECL 16; Total 45 pages, with 15 text, 30 exhibits.
    Written for a graduate system engineering course which emphasizes mathematical representation of system components and computer simulation of complex systems, this case has also found application in a civil engineering course on hydraulic machinery. The case begins with general discussion of the water power industry, then describes in some detail a particular hydroelectric power station, the Kings River Plant in California.
  - FMC Corporation, (A) Need for a Rice Sorter, (B) Rice Sorter Layout, (C) Mechanical Failures in a Rice Sorter, (D) Rice Sorter Redesign, K. H. Vesper, J. K. Williams, 1964; ECL 17; Total 96 pages (Parts A,B,C,D) with 22 text, 74 exhibits.
    Part A presents background in processed rice. Part B gives the concept selected by the company, carrying the story to the point where layout of a specific design is needed. Part C describes some problems which arose in the first machine. Part D tells how an FMC engineer went at the problems.
  - Oxford Laboratories, Prothrometer Design, R. H. McKim, J. K. Williams, 1964; ECL 18; Total 39 pages, with 20 text, 19 exhibits.
    An industrial design consultant, Robert H. McKim, has been asked to redesign a device for measuring blood clotting time (prothrometer), to improve its ease of assembly, ease of operation, and appearnace. The case is intended to give students practice in asking questions. It comes with a selection of additional handouts and with an Instructor's Note to respond to student questions asked about the general problems stated in this case.
  - Hewlett-Packard Company II, Mechanical Design of a Rotary Vane Microwave Attenuator, P. Z. Bulkeley, E. Echterling, Revised by Sue Hays, 1967; ECL 19; Total 13 pages (Parts A,B) with 4 text, 9 exhibits.
    In the first of two parts of this case, company engineers are faced with cracking in some shrink-fit parts of a rotary vane waveguide attenuator. Suitable as a problem in stress analysis. In Part B of the case, the Hewlett-Packard engineers have decided on the modification required to prevent cracking, and the remaining problem is to put dimensional tolerances on the parts, a problem suitable for freshman drawing. An Instructor's Note is included.
  - Hewlett-Packard Company IV, Component Layout of an Electronic Signal Analyzer, P. Z. Bulkeley, E. Echterling, 1964; ECL 20; Total 41 pages, with 8 text, 33 exhibits.
    Layout drawings are needed showing the arrangement with dimensions of electronic components and controls for a new model electronic signal analyzer. Intended as a problem for freshmen, its background illustrates the role of mechanical drawing in design of electronic equipment.
  - Hiller Aircraft Company I, Preliminary Design of a Light Observation Helicopter, P. Z. Bulkeley, E. Echterling, Revised 1968 by Richard C. Bourne., 1964; ECL 21; Total 38 pages, with 7 text, 31 exhibits.
    Intended as a simple design and sketching problem for freshmen, this case presents background of a major Hiller project in development of a new helicopter to compete for an Army contract for the largest single quantity of aircraft purchased since World War II. Description of how the project proceeds in the company and how compromises are required include by implication some of the constraints which the student should observe in his arrangement of major components and sketching of possible configurations.
  - Data International I, A Portable Sawmill, P. Z. Bulkeley, R. D. Regier, 1964; ECL 22; Total 35 pages, with 11 text, 24 exhibits.
    A letter has been received from a Colombian missionary expressing need for a lightweight portable machine for cutting logs into boards at stump site. Case intended to launch students into design projects of their own with minimal time wasted. Information on conventional sawmill practices and existing machinery plus some words of advice from experienced sawmill equipment designers are included.
  - Guy F. Atkinson Company, Clearance Between a Conveyor and Support Tower, H. O. Fuchs, R. D. Regier, Revised 1968 by Richard C. Bourne., 1965; ECL 23; Total 13 (Parts A,B) with 6 text, 7 exhibits.
    Two parts comprise this case. The first presents a problem in descriptive geometry to assure clearance between a conveyor and a tower over which it must pass at a skew angle. The other concerns design of a simple bracket for fastening one end of the conveyor. All events are taken from circumstances of a current California canal construction project. General aspects of the project are included in description of the background from which the problem emerges.
  - Lazer Hardware, Fred Moreno, 1972; Case 189: (Box 3)
  - Transportation of Liquefied Natural Gas, Sterling Beckwith, 1973; Case 198: (Box 3)
  - Amphibious Vehicle Models: Calibration and Testing, Al Nahas, 1973; Case 199: (Box 3)
  - 150 Ton Pipe: Easier To Make Than to Move, Al Nahas, 1973; Case 200: (Box 3)
  - Design of an Improved Aircraft Seat, R. Stephen Ball, William B. Goodman, William J. Kennish, 1973; Case 201: (Box 3)
  - Peterson Tractor, Albert J. Nahas, 1973; Case 205: (Box 3)
  - Air Force A-7D Brake Problem, H.O. Fuchs, 1974; Case 212: (Box 3)
  - Paul Hait and the Dental Unit, D. N. Howse, 1974; Case 213: (Box 3)
  - Designing a Gantry for Kyung Won, Professor H. O. Fuchs and Professor S. Bae, 1974; Case 215: (Box 3)
  - Difficulties with Modular Housing, G. Kardos, 1975; Case 219: (Box 3)
  - Thermal Fatigue and Instrument Design, Laurie Rendall, 1975; Case 221: (Box 3)
  - Measuring Motor Torque-Speed Curves, G. Kardos, A. Chuman, 1976; Case 222: (Box 3)
  - The 3.5 Millimetre Sliding Load, R. Sloss, 1960; Case 223: (Box 3)
  - Bart Dead Train Detection, O. Baskind, N. Y. N. Chu, J. A. Palomo, J. F. Rollings, 1976; Case 224: (Box 3)
  - The Story of Eighty-Four Minutes, J. P. Den Hartog, 1966; ECL 1001; Total 26 pages.
    A short elementary monograph by Professor Den Hartog on the special properties of a pendulum tuned to a period of eighty-four minutes and on the application of this device to navigation gyroscopes. Thirteen problems related to this pendulum are stated.
  - A Critical Meeting on the Development of Inertial Navigation-Related to The Story of 84 Minutes, W. Bollay, 1966; ECL 1002; Total 24 pages.
    Dr. Bollay's report on a confrontation between the proponents of guided missiles and a scientist who had declared such guided missiles to be impractical. A confrontation was arranged by the Secretary of the Air Force and resulted in changing the mind of the scientist.
  - Spin Stability of the Explorer Satellite, William Bollay, 1967; ECL 1006; Total 49 pages, 14 pages of charts and figures.
    This case relates a number of instructive events from the development of the highly successful Explorer satellite. It was designed to spin about its axis of minimum moment of inertia at a rate of about 700 RPM. But anomalies in the signals received from its antenna led to the conclusion that after about one orbit it changed to a rotation about its axis of maximum moment of inertia at a rate of about 120 RPM. Background and observed data are given in Part I. A dynamic analysis which explains the behavior is presented in Part II. Other interesting dynamic phenomena observed in the Explorer are discussed in Part III. The historical background is given in Part IV, documented by extracts from periodicals. The case includes a note for Instructors.
  - Ion Exchange Case Study, Arnold, John E. and R. S. Welther, M.I.T., 1955; ECL 1-4; Total 48 pages.
    State-of-the-art in ion exchange systems is described as background from which student design projects can be selected. A number of needs and problems are indicated to be awaiting solution.
  - Box Car Design Project, Arnold, John E., M.I.T., 1952; ECL 1-5; Total 16 pages with 10 text, 6 exhibits.
    Illustrates the state-of-the-art in boxcar construction, giving dimensional and other data on the cars and suggesting some disadvantages which may suggest a variety of possible design projects by students.
  - Sick Room Equipment, Arnold, John E. and G. H. Wood, M.I.T., 1956; ECL 1-6; Total 36 pages with 21 text, 15 exhibits.
    State-of-the-art in hospital beds, presenting background data on hospital beds as source material for student design projects. Students are to ferret out their own problems and then develop solutions.
  - Design of a Centrifuge Rotor Cap, P.C. Garg, 1969; Case 137: (Box 3)
  - Electric Beam Collimator, M.J. Lum, 1969; Case 138: (Box 3)
  - A Special Testing Problem at IBM, K. J. Waldron, 1970; Case 144: (Box 3)
  - Howard Arneson's Pool-Sweep, P.C. Garg, 1970; Case 146: (Box 3)
  - Design of a Ball Transfer Unit for Air Cargo, R. K. Ganeriwal, 1970; Case 149: (Box 3)
  - Drop Master, R. Ganeriwal, 1970; Case 150: (Box 3)
  - Underwater Pipeline, Dean C. Ing, 1970; Case 151: (Box 3)
  - Positioning a Microwave Diode, S. Hayes and R. Ganeriwal, 1970; Case 156: (Box 3)
  - Interfaces at Sterling Development Labaratories, Sue Hays, 1970; Case 157: (Box 3)
  - Jumping a Derrick, Professor Ralph J. Smith, 1970; Case 159: (Box 3)
  - Expansion of the Danville Pump Plant, James C. Collins, 1970; Case 160: (Box 3)
  - Development of a Stainless Steel Trashrack, R. J. Shuman, 1970; Case 161: (Box 3)
  - Variable Stability System of the X-14A VTOL Aircraft, J. Hill, G. Kardos, A. Winn, 1970; Case 162: (Box 3)
  - To Find a Bullet, Geza Kardos, 1971; Case 174: (Box 3)
  - Negligence, Drew V. Nelson, 1971; Case 178: (Box 3)
  - A Four Barrel Step-and-Repeat Camera, Geza Kardos, 1971; Case 181: (Box 3)
  - The Design of the Bart-AFC Barrier Drive System at IBM, R. Pizali, 1972; Case 185: (Box 3)
  - The Pickup-Head Link Failure, R. Pizali, 1972; Case 186: (Box 3)
  - Value Engineering Applied to an IBM Leveling Screw, R. Pizali, 1972; Case 187: (Box 3)
  - The Stun-Gun, A. P. Shack and G. Kardos, 1972; Case 188: (Box 3)
  - Precision Instrument Company, Modification of a Portable Video and Broadband Instrumentation Recorder, Karl H. Vesper and William H. Clemens, 1967; Case 76: (Box 2)
  - Hewlett-Packard VI, Signal Generator Read-Out Design, Karl H. Vesper, Robert Beardmore and Charles Fernald, 1967; Case 78: (Box 2)
  - Chaparral, Bolt Failure on a Racing Automobile, Henry O. Fuchs and William H. Clemens, 1967; Case 79: (Box 2)
  - Consolidated Dynamics Corporation, Fracture of a Marine Gear Rim, William H. Clemens, 1968; Case 80: (Box 2)
  - Design of an Electric Beam Dump at Stanford Linear Accelerator Center, Munir R. El-Saden, 1967; Case 82: (Box 2)
  - Shedding a Toroid Amplifier at Stanford Linear Accelerator Center, Sue Hays, 1967; Case 90: (Box 2)
  - Girder Alignment at Stanford Linear Accelerator Center, Henry O. Fuchs and Sue Hays, 1968; Case 91: (Box 2)
  - Development of a New Drill at Ingersoll-Rand Company, H.O. Fuchs and Ronald J. Shuman, 1967; Case 94: (Box 2)
  - Development of an Undersea Power Supply Aerojet General Corporation, William J. Clemens, 1967; Case 96: (Box 2)
  - Pump Plunger Improvements at Kobe Inc., Robert Martin, 1969; Case 100: (Box 2)
  - Development of a High Speed Weighing Machine at FMC, Sue Hays, 1969; Case 109: (Box 2)
  - Design of a Hand Operated Film Drive Mechanism, John Sondeno, 1969; Case 111: (Box 2)
  - The Go-Matic Accessory for Motorcycles, Prem Garg, 1969; Case 113: (Box 2)
  - Development of a Circular Strike Plate at Schlage Lock Company, Richard C. Bourne, 1968; Case 114: (Box 2)
  - Harvey La Branche: Spring Failures in a New Toy Rifle, Karl H. Vesper, 1968; Case 120: (Box 3)
  - Warren Deutsch: Design of a Satellite Controlling Instrument Panel, Mitchel Blanton, 1968; Case 124: (Box 3)
  - Plastic Pipe Saddle Design, Perm Garg, 1969; Case 126: (Box 3)
  - Three Years to Design a Door, Drew V. Nelson, 1969; Case 127: (Box 3)
  - Philco Corporation I, (A) Patient Room Door Handles, (B) Opening Sliding Glass Doors, (C) Surgical Instrument Cabinet Doors, (D) Label Dispenser Design, R. H. McKim, J.K. Williams, 1965; Case 25: (Box 1)
  - IBM II, Geneva Mechanism, K.H. Vesper., Case 26: (Box 1)
  - Hiller Aircraft Company II, (A) Design of a Supercharger Inlet Duct, (B) Filter Housing Clearance Considerations, (C) Structural Bracket Design, (D) Engine shroud Design, P.Z. Bulkeley, H.O. Fuchs, E.J. Echterling, 1964; Case 28: (Box 1)
  - Radiation Products Company, Failure of a Rotating Mirror, H.O. Fuchs, J. K. Williams, 1965; Case 30: (Box 1)
  - Precision Instrument Corporation, Experience with a Tape Reel Hold-down Mechanism, H.O. Fuchs, R.D. Regier, 1965; Case 31: (Box 1)
  - William Wohlfort, Design of a Variable Frequency Oscillator, R.E. Miller, W. Wohlfort, 1965; Case 35: (Box 1)
  - Allied Solid Rocket Corporation, E.J. Fisher, 1965; Case 37: (Box 1)
  - Dymo Industries, Inc., Design of a Typewriter Component, H.O. Fuchs, J.A. Alic, 1965; Case 38: (Box 1)
  - Rucker Company, (A) A Centrifuge Project, (B) Inertia Starter for the Centrifuge, (C) Centrifuge Clutch Design, H.O. Fuchs, O. Lorentsen, A. Krauter, 1965; Case 39: (Box 1)
  - Hughes Tool Company, Aircraft Division Development of a light Observation Helicopter for the United States Army, K.H. Vesper, E.J. Echterling, 1965; Case 41: (Box 2)
  - Gar Wood Industries, Inc. Failures at Welded Joints in a Hopper Trailer, H.O. Fuchs, J.A. Alic, 1965; Case 42: (Box 2)
  - Peterson Tractor Company, Design of a Side Sloper, H.O. Fuchs, J.A. Alic, revised by Richard C. Bourne, 1965 1968; Case 43: (Box 2)
  - Dynasham Truck Company, Ltd., Truck Suspension Bolt and Bushing Failures, H.O. Fuchs, J.A. Alic, 1966; Case 44: (Box 2)
  - Marvetti, Inc., Design and Development of a Printing Calculator, H.O. Fuchs, J.A. Alic, 1966; Case 45: (Box 2)
  - Beckman and Whitley, Inc. I, Design of a 16mm Portable News Film Camera, H.O. Fuchs, D.A. Horine, Revised by Richard C. Bourne, 1966 1968; Case 46: (Box 2)
  - Hoover Dam, H.O. Fuchs, P. Searles, UCLA, 1964; Case 1-17: (Box 1)
  - Selected Design Notes, reproduced from the Flight Safety Foundation., Case 1-16: (Box 1)
  - The Story of Eight-Four Minutes, J.P. Den Hartog, 1966; Case 1001: (Box 1)
  - A Critical Meeting on the Development of Inertial Navigation-Related to The Story of 84 Minutes, W. Bollay, 1966; Case 1002: (Box 1)
  - Spin Stability of the Explorer Satellite, William Bollay, 1967; Case 1006: (Box 1)
  - Hewlett-Packard Company I, (A) Mechanical Design of Coaxial Microwave Connectors, (B) History of Coaxial Microwave Connector design, K.H. Vesper, (C) Commercial Development of the Sexless Connector by Amphenol Corporation, Sue Hays, 1964, 1967; Case 1: (Box 1)
  - Hewlett-Packard Company III, (A) Drill Jig Design for a Structural Plate, (B) Drill Jig Tolerances, P.Z. Bulkeley, E. Echterling, 1964; Case 15: (Box 1)
  - Pacific Gas and Electric Company, Digital Computer Simulation of a Hydroelectric Plant, R.E. Keller, R.D. Regier, 1964; Case 16: (Box 1)
  - FMC Corporation, (A) Need for a Rice Sorter, (B) Rice Sorter Layout, (C) Mechanical Failures in a Rice Sorter, (D) Rice Sorter Redesign, K.H. Vesper, J.K. Williams, 1964; Case 17: (Box 1)
  - Oxford Laboratories, Prothrometer Design, R.H. McKim, J.K. Williams, 1964; Case 18: (Box 1)
  - Hewlett-Packard Company II, Mechanical Design of a Rotary Vane Microwave Attenuator, P.Z. Bulkeley, E. Echterling, Revised by Sue Hays, 1967; Case 19: (Box 1)
  - Hewlett-Packard Company IV, Component Layout of an Electronic Signal Analyzer, P.Z. Bulkeley, E. Echterling, 1964; Case 20: (Box 1)
  - Hiller Aircraft Company I, Preliminary Design of a Light Observation Helicopter, P.Z. Bulkeley, E. Echterling, Revised 1968 by Richard C. Bourne., 1964; Case 21: (Box 1)
  - Data International I, A Portable Sawmill, P. Z. Bulkeley, R.D. Regier, 1964; Case 22: (Box 1)
  - Guy F. ATkinson Company, Clearance Between a Conveyor and Support Tower, H.O. Fuchs, R.D. Regier, Revised 1968 by Richard C. Bourne., 1965; Case 23: (Box 1)
  - Ion Exchange Case Study, Arnold, John E. and R. S. Welther, M.I.T., 1955; Case 1-4: (Box 1)
  - Box Car Design Project, Arnold, John E., M.I.T., undated; Case 1-5: (Box 1)
  - Sick Room Equipment, Arnold, John E. and G.H. Wood, M.I.T., 1956; Case 1-6: (Box 1)
  - Arcturus IV, Arnold, John E., M.I.T., 1953; Case 1-7: (Box 1)
  - Ceres Project, Arnold, John E., H. W. Babcock, E. L. Davis, M.I.T., 1954; Case 1-8: (Box 1)
  - Rice in Burma, Arnold, John E., A.T. Ling, M.I.T., 1953; Case 1-9: (Box 1)
  - Zylerium Blindness, Arnold, John E., Stanford., Case 1-10: (Box 1)
  - Chinese typewriter, Arnold, John E. and A.T. Ling, M.I.T., 1952; Case 1-11: (Box 1)
  - Telephone Information Service, Need for a Better Directory System, Arnold, John E., Stanford, 1959; Case 1-12: (Box 1)
  - Development of an Oil Well Tubing Stripper Rubber, P.E. Bickel, H.O. Fuchs, UCLA, 1964; Case 1-13: (Box 1)
  - The Wright Brothers's Airplane, H.O. Fuchs, UCLA, 1964; Case 1-14: (Box 1)
  - Design and Development of an Automatic Refrigerator Car Heater, H.O. Fuchs, UCLA, 1963; Case 1-15: (Box 1)